Okay, this morning I'm speaking
حسنا، هذا الصباح سوف أتكلم
on the question of corruption.
فيما يتعلق بمسألة الفساد.
And corruption is defined
وهو تعريف الفساد
as the abuse of a position of trust
هو الإساءة لموضع ثقة
for the benefit of yourself -- or, in the case of our context,
لمنفعة نفسك--أو، في حالة سياقنا،
your friends, your family or your financiers.
أصدقائك أو عائلتك أو مموليك.
Okay? Friends, family and financiers.
حسنا؟ الأسرة والأصدقاء والممولين.
But we need to understand what we understand about corruption,
ولكن نحن بحاجة إلى فهم ما نعرفه عن الفساد،
and we need to understand that
ونحن بحاجة إلى أن نفهم أنه
we have been miseducated about it, and we have to admit that.
قد تم تعليمنا بشكل خاطىء حول هذا الموضوع، وعلينا أن نعترف بذلك.
We have to have the courage to admit that
ويجب أن تكون لدينا الشجاعة لنعترف بأنه
to start changing how we deal with it.
للبدء في تغيير كيفية التعامل مع هذا الموضوع.
The first thing is that the big myth, number one,
أول شيء هو أن الخرافة الكبيرة، رقم واحد،
is that in fact it's not really a crime.
هي أن الفساد في الواقع ليس حقاً جريمة.
When we get together with friends and family
عندما نجتمع مع الأهل والأصدقاء
and we discuss crime in our country,
و نناقش الجريمة في بلدنا،
crime in Belmont or crime in Diego or crime in Marabella,
الجريمة في بلمونت أو الجريمة في دييغو أو الجريمة في مارابيلا،
nobody's speaking about corruption.
لا أحد يتحدث عن الفساد.
That's the honest truth.
هذا هي الحقيقة الصريحة.
When the Commissioner of Police comes on TV to talk about crime,
عندما يأتي "مفوض من الشرطة" على شاشة التلفزيون للحديث عن الجريمة،
he isn't speaking about corruption.
و هو لا يتحدث عن الفساد.
And we know for sure when the Minister of National Security
ونحن نعلم عن يقين عندما "وزير الأمن الوطني"
is speaking about crime, he's not talking about corruption either.
يتحدث عن الجريمة، لم يتحدث عن الفساد أيضاً.
The point I'm making is that it is a crime.
النقطة التى أوضحها هي أن الفساد جريمة.
It is an economic crime, because we're involving the looting of taxpayers' money.
أنها جريمة اقتصادية، لأننا نتشارك على نهب أموال دافعي الضرائب.
Public and private corruption is a reality.
الفساد في القطاعين العام والخاص حقيقة واقعة.
As somebody who comes from the private sector,
كشخص قادم من القطاع الخاص،
I can tell you there's a massive amount of corruption
أستطيع أن أقول لكم هناك كمية هائلة من الفساد
in the private sector that has nothing to do with government.
في القطاع الخاص الذي لا علاقة له بالحكومة.
The same bribes and backhanders and things that take place under the table,
نفس الرشاوي والأمور التي تجري تحت الطاولة،
it all takes place in the private sector.
كلها تحدث في القطاع الخاص.
Today, I'm focusing on public sector corruption,
واليوم، سوف أركز على الفساد في القطاع العام،
which the private sector also participates in.
والتي يشارك فيها القطاع الخاص أيضاً.
The second important myth to understand --
الخرافة المهمة الثانية -
because we have to destroy these myths,
لأنه يجب علينا القضاء على هذه الخرافات،
dismantle them and destroy them and ridicule them --
تفكيكها وتدميرها، والسخرية منها-
the second important myth to understand
الخرافة الثانية المهمة
is the one that says
هي التي تقول
that in fact corruption is only a small problem --
أن الفساد في الواقع مجرد مشكلة صغيرة-
if it is a problem, it's only a small problem,
إذا كان هناك مشكلة، أنها فقط مشكلة صغيرة،
that in fact it's only a little 10 or 15 percent,
أنها في الحقيقة فقط القليل من 10 أو 15 في المائة،
it's been going on forever, it probably will continue forever,
هذا يحدث منذ القدم، ربما سوف تستمر إلى الأبد،
and there's no point passing any laws, because there's little we can do about it.
وليس هناك غاية لفرض أي قوانين، لأنه ليس هناك الكثير مما يمكننا القيام به حيال ذلك.
And I want to demonstrate that that, too,
وأريد أن أثبت أن ذلك، أيضا،
is a dangerous myth, very dangerous.
خرافة خطيرة ، خطيرة جداً.
It's a piece of public mischief.
أنها جزء من الأذى العام
And I want to speak a little bit,
وأنا أريد أن أتكلم قليلاً،
take us back about 30 years.
تأخذ بنا إلى الوراء حوالي 30 عاماً.
We're coming out today from Trinidad and Tobago,
نحن نخرج اليوم من ترينيداد وتوباغو،
a resource-rich, small Caribbean country,
بلد الكاريبي الصغيرة، والغنية بالموارد،
and in the early 1970s we had a massive increase in the country's wealth,
وفي أوائل السبعينات شهدنا زيادة هائلة في ثروة البلاد،
and that increase was caused by the increase in world oil prices.
وتلك الزيادة ناجمه عن الزيادة في أسعار النفط العالمية.
We call them petrodollars. The treasury was bursting with money.
سميناهم عائدات النفط. كانت الخزانة مملؤة بالمال.
And it's ironic, because
أنها مفارقة، لأن
we're standing today in the Central Bank.
نحن نقف اليوم في البنك المركزي.
You see, history's rich in irony.
كما ترون، التاريخ غني بالمفارقات.
and the Central Bank is responsible for a lot of the things I'm going to be speaking about.
والمصرف المركزي المسؤول عن الكثير من الأشياء التي سوف أتحدث عنها.
Okay? We're talking about irresponsibility in public office.
حسنا؟ نحن نتحدث عن إنعدام المسؤولية في الوظائف العامة.
We're speaking about the fact that across the terrace,
ونتحدث عن حقيقة أنه عبر الشرفة،
the next tower is the Ministry of Finance,
البرج المجاور هو وزارة المالية،
and there's a lot of connection with us today,
وهناك الكثير من الروابط معنا اليوم،
so we're speaking within your temple today. Okay?
لذلك نحن نتحدث داخل المعبد الخاص بك اليوم. حسنا؟
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
The first thing I want to talk about is that
أول شيء أريد أن أتحدث عنه
when all of this money flowed into our country about 40 years ago,
عندما كل هذه الأموال تدفقت إلى بلادنا قبل مايقارب 40 سنة
we embarked, the government of the day embarked
شرعنا،- الحكومة التي كانت وقتها- شرعت
on a series of government-to-government arrangements
في ترتيبات مابين حكومة الى حكومة
to have rapidly develop the country.
لتطوير البلاد بسرعة.
And some of the largest projects in the country
وبعض من أكبر المشاريع في البلد
were being constructed through government-to-government arrangements
شُيدت من خلال الترتيبات ما بين الحكومات
with some of the leading countries in the world,
مع بعض البلدان الرائدة في العالم،
the United States and Britain and France and so on and so on.
الولايات المتحدة وبريطانيا وفرنسا وما شابه وما شابه.
As I said, even this building we're standing in -- that's one of the ironies --
وكما قلت، حتى هذا المبنى ونحن واقفين عليه--واحدة من المفارقات-
this building was part of that series of complexes,
وكان هذا المبنى جزءاً من تلك السلسلة من المجمعات،
what they called the Twin Towers.
ما أسموه البرجين التوأمين.
It became so outrageous, the whole situation,
أصبحت أمر فظيع، كل الوضع برمته،
that in fact a commission of inquiry was appointed,
أنه في الواقع قد تم تعيين لجنة تحقيق،
and it reported in 1982, 30 years ago it reported --
قدمت تقريرا عام 1982، قبل 30 عاماً-
the Ballah Report -- 30 years ago,
تقرير بالاه -- قبل 30 عاماً،
and immediately the government-to-government arrangements were stopped.
وعلى الفور تم إيقاف ترتيبات الحكومة للحكومة.
The then-Prime Minister went to Parliament
وذهب رئيس الوزراء في ذلك الوقت إلى البرلمان
to give a budget speech, and he said some things that I'll never forget.
ليلقي خطاباً عن الميزانية، وقال بعض الأشياء التي سوف لن أنساها ابدأ.
They went right in here. I was a young man at the time.
أتوا هنا. كنت شاب في ذلك الوقت.
It went right into my heart.
دخلت مباشرة إلى قلبي.
And he said that, in fact — Let me see if this thing works.
وقال، في الواقع، دعوني أرى ما إذا كان يعمل هذا الشيء.
Are we getting a, yeah?—
هل نصل إلى، نعم؟-
That's what he told us.
وهذا ما قاله لنا.
He told us that, in fact,
قال لنا أنه، في الواقع،
two out of every three dollars of our petrodollars
اثنان من أصل كل ثلاثة دولارات من دولارت البترول لدينا
that we spent, the taxpayers' money,
التي صرفت، و أموال دافعي الضرائب،
was wasted or stolen.
قد ُضيعت أو سُرقت.
So the 10 or 15 percent is pure mischief.
ولذلك 10 أو 15 في المائة من الخسارة الكاملة.
As we say, it's a nancy-story. Forget it.
وكما نقول، هي قصة نانسي. لا عليك.
That's for little children. We are big people,
هذا للأطفال الصغار. نحن شعب كبير،
and we're trying to deal with what's happening in our society.
ونحن نسعى للتعامل مع ما يحدث في مجتمعنا.
Okay? This is the size of the problem.
حسنا؟ هذا هو حجم المشكلة.
Okay? Two thirds of the money stolen or wasted.
حسنا؟ ثلثي الأموال اما مسروقة أو مهدرة.
That was 30 years ago. 1982 was Ballah.
التي كانت قبل 30 عاماً. في عام 1982كان بالاه.
So what has changed?
ما الذي تغير؟
I don't like to bring up embarrassing secrets
أنا لا أحب إحضار أسرار محرجة
to an international audience, but I have to.
لجمهور دولي، ولكن لا بد لي من ذلك.
Four months ago, we suffered a constitutional outrage in this country.
منذ أربعة أشهر، عانينا من غضب دستوري في هذا البلد.
We call it the Section 34 fiasco, the Section 34 fiasco,
نسميها قسم الفشل الذريع 34، قسم 34 الفشل الذريع،
a suspicious piece of law, and I'm going to say it like it is,
قطعة مشبوهة من القانون، وأنا سأقول الحقيقة كما هي،
a suspicious piece of law
قطعة مشبوهة للقانون
was passed at a suspicious time
وصدرت في وقت مشبوه
to free some suspects. (Laughter)
لتحرير بعض المشتبه فيهم. (ضحك)
And it was called, those people are called
وكان يطلق عليه، هؤلاء الناس يسمون
the Piarco Airport accused.
متهمي مطار بياركو
I'm going to have my own lexicon speaking here today.
سوف أجعل كلماتي تتحدث هنا اليوم.
They are the Piarco Airport accused.
هم متهمي مطار بياركو.
It was a constitutional outrage of the first order,
كان غضب دستورياً من الدرجة الأولى،
and I have labeled it the Plot to Pervert Parliament.
و قد وصفتها بأنها مؤامرة "تضليل البرلمان".
Our highest institution in our country was perverted.
أعلى مؤسسة في بلدنا كانت منحرفة.
We are dealing with perverts here
أننا نتعامل مع منحرفين هنا
of an economic and financial nature.
ذو طابع إقتصادي ومالي.
Do you get how serious this problem is?
هل تعرف مدى خطورة هذه المشكلة؟
There was massive protest. A lot of us in this room
كان هناك احتجاج واسع النطاق. الكثير منا في هذه القاعة
took part in the protest in different forms.
شارك في هذه المظاهرة بأشكال مختلفة.
Most importantly, the American embassy complained,
الأهم من ذلك، اشتكت السفارة الأمريكية،
so Parliament was swiftly reconvened,
لذا انعقد البرلمان سريعاً،
and the law was reversed, it was repealed.
وأُلغى القانون، أُبطل.
That's the word lawyers use. It was repealed.
تلك هي الكلمة يستخدمها المحامين. أُبطل.
But the point is
ولكن النقطة
that Parliament was outwitted in the whole course of events,
أن البرلمان كان يحتالون في كامل مسار الأحداث،
because what really happened is that,
لأن ما حدث فعلا هو،
because of the suspicious passage of that law,
بسبب مرور مشبوه لذلك القانون،
the law was actually passed into effect
وأصبح القانون فعلاً حيز التنفيذ
on the weekend we celebrated our 50th anniversary of independence,
في عطلة نهاية الأسبوع التي فيها أحتفلنا بالذكرى الخمسين للاستقلال،
our jubilee of independence.
اليوبيل الذهبي للاستقلال لدينا.
So that is the kind of outrage of the thing.
ذلك هو نوعٌ من الغضب على شيء.
It was kind of a nasty way to get maturation, but we got it,
كانت طريقة سيئة للحصول على النضج، ولكن حصلنا عليها،
because we all understood it,
لأننا جميعاً فهمناها،
and for the first time that I could remember,
و للمرة الأولى التي أستطيع فيها أن أتذكر،
there were mass protests against this corruption.
كانت هناك احتجاجات جماهيرية ضد هذا الفساد.
And that gave me a lot of hope. Okay?
وهذا قدم لي الكثير من الأمل. حسنا؟
Those of us who are, sometimes you feel like
بعض منا، في بعض الأحيان تشعر بأنك
you're a little bit on your own doing some of this work.
قمت قليلاً ببعض هذه الأعمال.
That passage of the law and the repeal of the law
ذلك الإقرار للقانون وإلغاءه
fortified the case of the Piarco Airport accused.
تحصين حالة متهمين مطار بياركو.
So it was one of those really superior double bluff kind of things that took place.
لذا كانت واحده من هذه النوع من ازدواجية الخدع الماكرة حقاً مما حصل.
But what were they accused of?
ولكن مالذي كانوا متهمون به؟
What was it that they were accused of?
ما هو الشيء الذي أُتهمه فيه؟
I'm being a bit mysterious for those of you out there. What were they accused of?
أنا غامضٌ بعض الشيء عليكم. ما كانوا متهمون به؟
We were trying to build, or reconstruct largely,
كنا نحاول بناء، أو إعادة بناء إلى حد كبير،
an airport that had grown outdated.
مطار عفى عليه الزمن.
The entire project cost about 1.6 billion dollars,
تكلفة المشروع بأكمله حوالي 1.6 مليار دولار،
Trinidad and Tobago dollars,
دولارت ترينيداد وتوباغو،
and in fact, we had a lot of bid-rigging
وفي الواقع، كان لدينا الكثير من التلاعب بالعطاءات
and suspicious activity, corrupt activity took place.
ونشاط مشبوه، وحدث النشاط الفاسد.
And to get an idea of what it consisted of,
وللحصول على فكرة عن ما هذا الفساد متكون من،
and to put it in context in relationship to this whole
ووضعها في السياق مع علاقة كلها هذا
second myth about it being no big thing,
الخرافة الثانية كونها ليس بالشيء الكبير،
we can look at this second slide here.
يمكننا أن ننظر إلى هذه الشريحة الثانية هنا.
And what we have here -- I am not saying so,
وماذا لدينا هنا--أنا لا أقول ذلك،
this is the Director of Public Prosecutions in a written statement. He said so.
هذا هو "مدير النيابات العامة" في بيان مكتوب. هو قال ذلك.
And he's telling us that for the $1.6 billion cost of the project,
وهو يقول لنا أن تكلفة المشروع 1.6 مليار دولار ،
one billion dollars has been traced
وقد تم تتبع مليار دولار
to offshore bank accounts.
إلى حسابات مصرفية في الخارج.
One billion dollars of our taxpayers' money
1 مليار دولار من أموال دافعي الضرائب لدينا
has been located in offshore bank accounts.
تم ايداعها في حسابات مصرفية في الخارج.
Being the kind of suspicious person I am,
وكوني شخص مشكك،
I am outraged at that, and I'm going to pause here,
أشعر بالغضب في ذلك، و سوف أوقف هنا،
I'm going to pause now and again and bring in different things.
سوف أتوقف الآن، ومرة أخرى، و أتكلم عن أمور مختلفة.
I'm going to pause here and bring in something I saw
سوف أتوقف هنا وأتكلم عن شيء رأيته
in November last year at Wall Street. I was at Zuccotti Park.
في تشرين الثاني/نوفمبر من العام الماضي في وول ستريت. كنت في حديقة زوكوتي.
It was autumn. It was cool. It was damp. It was getting dark.
كان الوقت خريف. وكان الجو رائع, رطب. وكان الوقت متأخر.
And I was walking around with the protesters
وكنت أتجول مع المتظاهرين
looking at the One Wall Street, Occupy Wall Street movement walking around.
أنظر في "شارع الوال"، وحركة "احتلال وول ستريت" يتجولون.
And there was a lady with a sign, a very simple sign,
وكان هناك سيدة بلافتة، لافتة بسيطة جداً،
a kind of battered-looking blonde lady,
كانت السيدة شقراء،
and the sign was made out of Bristol board, as we say in these parts,
وكانت اللافتة مصنوعة من لوح البريستول، كما نقول في هذه الأجزاء،
and it was made with a marker.
وكانت مكتوب عليها بقلم.
And what it said on that sign hit me right in the center.
وما كان مكتوب على اللافتة جذبني.
It said, "If you're not outraged, you haven't been paying attention."
تقول اللافتة، "إذا لم تغضب، فأنت لم تكن متيقظاً."
If you're not outraged by all of this, you haven't been paying attention.
إذا لم تكن غاضباً من كل هذا، فأنت لم تكن متيقظاً.
So listen up, because we're getting into even deeper waters.
لذا أستمع، نظراً لأننا نخوض في مياه أكثر عمقاً.
My brain started thinking.
بدأ ذهني بالتفكير.
Well, what if --
حسناً، ماذا لو-
because I'm suspicious like that. I read a lot of spy novels and stuff.
لأنني مشكك. قرأت الكثير من روايات التجسس وغيرها.
What if -- (Laughter)
ماذا لو-(ضحك)
But to make it in these wrongs,
ولكن لجعلها أخطاء،
you have to read a lot of spy novels
يجب عليك لقراءة الكثير من الروايات التجسس
and follow some of that stuff, right? (Laughter)
وتتبع بعض من تلك الأشياء، صحيح؟ (ضحك)
But what if this wasn't the first time?
ولكن ماذا لو لم تكن هذه أول مرة؟
What if this is just the first time
ما إذا لو كانت هذه المرة الأولى فقط
that the so-and-sos had been caught?
وهذا وهذا تم إكتشافه ؟
What if it had happened before? How would I find out?
ما إذا لو قد حدثت من قبل؟ كيف أعرف؟
Now, the previous two examples I gave
الآن، المثالين السابقين الذيّن ضربتهما
were to do with construction sector corruption, okay?
كانا متعلقين بالفساد في قطاع البناء، حسنا؟
And I have the privilege at this time
ويشرفني في هذا الوقت
to lead the Joint Consultative Council, which is a not-for-profit.
لقيادة "المجلس الاستشاري المشترك"، والذي هو منظمة لا تهدف الى الربح.
We're at jcc.org.tt, and we have the -- we are the leaders
نحن في jcc.org.tt، ولدينا--نحن الزعماء
in the struggle to produce a new public procurement system
في النضال من أجل إنتاج نظام جديد للمشتريات العامة
about how public money is transacted.
حول كيف يتم حوالة المال العام .
So those of you interested in finding out more about it,
لذا للذين مهتمين منكم في العثور على مزيد من المعلومات حول هذا الموضوع،
or joining us or signing up on any of our petitions, please get involved.
أو الانضمام إلينا أو التوقيع على أي من المعاريض لدينا، الرجاء المشاركة.
But I'm going to segue to another thing that relates,
ولكن سوف أتبع إلى شيء آخر ذو علاقة ،
because one of my private campaigns I've been conducting
لأن واحدة من الحملات الخاصة التي قمت بها
for over three and a half years
لما يزيد على ثلاثة ونصف سنة
is for transparency and accountability
للشفافية والمساءلة
around the bailout of CL Financial.
حول إنقاذ مجموعة CL المالية.
CL Financial is the Caribbean's largest ever conglomerate, okay?
مجموعة CL المالية هي أكبر مجموعة كريبيه؟
And without getting into all of the details,
ودون الدخول في كل التفاصيل،
it is said to have collapsed — I'm using my words very carefully —
يقال أنها انهارت — أنا باستخدام كلماتي بعناية شديدة-
it's said to have collapsed in January of '09,
قد قيل انها أنهارت في كانون الثاني/يناير ' 2009
which is just coming up to nearly four years.
والذي يكاد يكون أربع سنوات.
In an unprecedented fit of generosity --
في تناسب لم يسبق لها مثيل من الكرم-
and you have to be very suspicious about these people --
ويجب عليك أن تكون مشكك للغاية حول هؤلاء الناس-
in an unprecedented — and I'm using that word carefully —
في حال لم يسبق له مثيل، وأنا أستخدام تلك الكلمة بعناية —
unprecedented fit of generosity, the government of the day
تناسب لم يسبق لها مثيل من الكرم، الحكومة اليوم
signed, made a written commitment, to repay all of the creditors.
وقعت، تعهد مكتوب، بتسديد جميع الدائنين.
And I can tell you without fear of contradiction
وأستطيع أن أقول لكم من دون خوف من التناقض
that hasn't happened anywhere else on the planet.
هذا لم يحدث في أي مكان آخر على هذا الكوكب.
Let's understand, because we lack context.
دعونا نفهم، لأننا نفتقر إلى السياق.
People are telling us it's just like Wall Street. It's not just like Wall Street.
الناس تقول لنا أنها مجرد مثل وول ستريت. أنها ليست مجرد مثل وول ستريت.
Trinidad and Tobago is like a place with different laws of physics or biology or something.
ترينيداد وتوباغو يشبه مكاناً مع وجود قوانين مختلفة في الفيزياء أو علم الأحياء أو شيء من هذا.
It's not just like anywhere. (Applause)
أنها ليست مثل أي مكان. (تصفيق)
It's not just like anywhere. It's not just like anywhere.
أنها ليست مثل أي مكان. أنها ليست مثل أي مكان.
Here is here, and out there is out there. Okay?
هنا هو هنا، ومن هناك إلى هناك. حسنا؟
I'm serious now.
أنا جاد الآن.
Listen. They've had bailouts on Wall Street.
استمعوا. لقد حصلوا على كفالات في وول ستريت.
They've had bailouts in London.
لقد حصلوا على كفالات في لندن.
They've had bailouts in Europe.
لقد حصلوا في كفالات في أوروبا.
In Africa, they've had bailouts. In Nigeria, six of the major
في أفريقيا، لقد حصلوا على كفالات. وفي نيجيريا، ستة من
commercial banks collapsed at the same time as ours, eh?
المصارف التجارية الرئيسية قد انهارت في نفس الوقت كبلدنا، أييه؟
It's interesting to parallel how the Nigerian experience has --
أنه لمشوق لموازاة كيف كانت التجربة النيجيرية-
how they've treated it, and they've treated it
كيف تعاملوا معها، كيف تعاملوا معها
very well compared to us.
بشكل جيد مقارنة بالنسبة لنا.
Nowhere on the planet
لا مكان على كوكب الأرض
have all the creditors been bailed out
جميع الدائنين تتم كفالتهم
in excess of what their statutory entitlements were.
بالإضافة لمستحقاتهم القانونية.
Only here. So what was the reason for the generosity?
فقط هنا. لذا فما هو سبب الكرم؟
Is our government that generous? And maybe they are.
هل حكومتنا سخية ؟ ربما هم هكذا.
Let's look at it. Let's look into it.
دعونا ننظر في الأمر. دعونا ننظر في الأمر.
So I started digging and writing and so and so on,
وهكذا بدأت البحث و الكتابة وهلم جرا،
and that work can be found, my personal work
و ذالك العمل يمكن الاطلاع عليه، عملي الشخصي
can be found at AfraRaymond.com, which is my name.
يمكن الإطلاع عليه على AfraRaymond.com، الذي هو اسمي.
It's a not-for-profit blog that I run.
أنها مدونة--غير ربحية والتي أديرها.
Not as popular as some of the other people, but there you go.
ليست لها شعبية كما هي مدونات بعض الناس الآخرين،
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But the point is that the bitter experience of Section 34,
لكن النقطة المهمة هي أن التجربة المريرة من قسم 34،
that plot to pervert Parliament, that bitter experience
تلك المؤامرة لتضليل البرلمان، تلك التجربة المريرة
that took place in August,
التي وقعت في آب/أغسطس،
when we were supposed to be celebrating our independence,
عندما كان من المفترض أن نحتفل بحصولنا على الاستقلال،
going into September, forced me to check myself
حلول أيلول/سبتمبر، اجبرني لفحص نفسي
and recalculate my bearings,
وإعادة حساب مواقفي،
and to go back into some of the work, some of the stuff I'd written
و بالعودة إلى بعض الأعمال، بعض الأشياء التي كتبت
and some of the exchanges I'd had with the officials
وبعض التبادلات مع المسؤولين
to see what was really what.
لمعرفة ما كان حقاً ما.
As we say in Trinidad and Tobago, who is who and what is what?
وكما نقول في ترينيداد وتوباغو، من هو من، وماذا هو ماذا؟
Okay? We want to try to recalculate.
حسنا؟ نحن نريد أن نحاول إعادة حساب.
And I made a Freedom of Information application
وأنا صنعت تطبيق "حرية الإعلام"
in May this year to the Ministry of Finance.
في أيار/مايو من هذا العام إلى وزارة المالية.
The Ministry of Finance is the next tower over.
وزارة المالية هي البرج المجاور.
This is the other context.
هذا السياق الأخر.
The Ministry of Finance, we are told,
وزارة المالية، قيل لنا،
is subject to the provisions of the Freedom of Information Act.
يخضع لأحكام "قانون حرية المعلومات".
I'm going to take you through a worked example of whether that's really so.
سوف أطلعكم على مثال عملي لما إذا كان هذا حقاً ذلك.
The Central Bank in which we stand this morning
المصرف المركزي الذي نقف عليه هذا الصباح
is immune from the provisions of the Freedom of Information Act.
بمنأى عن أحكام "قانون حرية المعلومات".
So in fact, you can't ask them anything,
حتى في الواقع، أنت لا يمكن أن نطلب منهم أي شيء،
and they don't have to answer anything.
وليس لديهم الإجابة على أي شيء.
That is the law since 1999.
وذلك قانون منذ عام 1999.
So I plunged into this struggle, and I asked four questions.
لذا أقحمتُ نفسي في هذا النضال، وسألت أربعة أسئلة.
And I'll relate the questions to you in the short form with the reply,
سوف أربط الأسئلة لكم بشكل مختصر مع الرد،
so you could understand, as I said, where we are.
حتى يمكنكم الفهم، كما قلت، المكان الذي نحن فيه .
Here is not like anywhere else.
هنا ليس مثل أي مكان آخر.
Question number one:
السؤال رقم واحد:
I asked to see the accounts of CL Financial,
طلبت أن انظر الحسابات البنكية للمجوعة المالية CL،
and if you can't show me the accounts --
إذا كنتم لا تستطيعون إطلاعي على الحسابات-
the Minister of Finance is making statements,
وزير المالية يدلي بتصريحات،
passing new laws and giving speeches and so on.
يصدر قوانين جديدة ويقدم خطابات وهلم جرا.
What are the figures he's relying on?
ما هي الأرقام التي يعتمد عليها؟
It's like that joke: I want whatever he's drinking.
أنها مثل تلك نكتة: أريد ما يشربه هو.
And they wrote back and said to me,
وردوا علي وقالوا لي،
well what do you really mean?
حسنا ماذا حقاً تقصد؟
So they hit my question with a question.
حيث قاموا بالرد على سؤالي بسؤال.
Second point: I want to see
النقطة الثانية: أريد أن أعرف
who are the creditors of the group who have been repaid?
من هم الدائنون للمجموعة الذين قاموا بالسداد؟
Let me pause here to point out to you all
واسمحوا لي أن أتوقف هنا لأشير لكم جميعا
that 24 billion dollars of our money has been spent on this.
أنه تم أنفاق 24 مليار دولار من أموالنا على هذا.
That is about three and a half billion U.S. dollars
وهذا حوالي ثلاثة ونصف مليار دولار أمريكي
coming out of a small -- we used to be resource-rich --
أخرجت من دولة - اعتادت أن تكون غنية بالموارد-
Caribbean country. Okay?
صغيره في منطقة البحرالكاريبي. حسنا؟
And I asked the question,
وسألت السؤال،
who was getting that three and a half billion dollars?
من هم الذين حصلوا على تلك الثلاثة ونصف مليار دولار؟
And I want to pause again to bring up context,
وأريد أن أتوقف مرة أخرى لإحضار السياق،
because context helps us to get clarity understanding this thing.
لأن السياق يساعدنا للحصول على فهم واضح هذا الشيء.
There's a particular individual who is in the government now.
يوجد هناك فرد بعينه هو الآن في الحكومة.
The name of the person doesn't matter.
لا يهم اسم الشخص.
And that person made a career
وحصل هذا الشخص على مهنة
out of using the Freedom of Information Act
من استخدام "قانون حرية المعلومات"
to advance his political cause.
للنهوض بقضيته السياسية.
Okay? His name isn't important.
حسنا؟ اسمه ليس مهما.
I wouldn't dignify it. I'm on a point.
لا أود تبجيله. لدي نقطة.
The point is, that person made a career out of using
النقطة هي، أن ذلك الشخص حصل على مهنة من إستخدام
the Freedom of Information Act to advance his cause.
"قانون حرية المعلومات" للنهوض بقضيته.
And the most famous case
والحالة الأكثر شهرة
was what we came to call the Secret Scholarship Scandal,
ما سميناه "فضيحة المنح الدراسية السرية"،
where in fact there was about 60 million dollars in government money
حيث في الواقع كان هناك حوالي 60 مليون دولار في إيرادات الحكومة
that had been dispersed in a series of scholarships,
التي تفرقت في سلسلة من المنح الدراسية،
and the scholarships hadn't been advertised, and so and so on and so on.
ولم يُعلن عن هذه المنح الدراسية، وهكذا وهلم جرا وهلم جرا.
And he was able to get the court, using that act of Parliament,
وكان قادراً على الذهاب إالى المحكمة، واستخدام قانون البرلمان،
Freedom of Information Act,
قانون حرية المعلومات،
to release the information,
للإفراج عن المعلومات،
and I thought that was excellent.
وأعتقدت أن ذلك كانت ممتازاً.
Fantastic.
رائعاً.
But you see, the question is this:
ولكن السؤال هو:
If it's right and proper for us to use the Freedom of Information Act
إذا كان من الصحيح و مناسب لنا إستخدام "قانون حرية المعلومات"
and to use the court
واللجوء إلى المحكمة
to force a disclosure about 60 million dollars in public money,
لفرض الكشف عن حوالي 60 مليون دولار من الأموال العامة،
it must be right and proper
يجب أن تكون صحيحة و مناسب
for us to force a disclosure about 24 billion dollars.
بالنسبة لنا لفرض الكشف عن حوالي 24 مليار دولار.
You see? But the Ministry of Finance,
فهمتم؟ لكن وزارة المالية،
the Permanent Secretary of the Ministry of Finance,
الأمين الدائم لوزارة المالية،
wrote me and said to me, that information is exempt too.
كتب لي وقال لي، أن المعلومات معفاة أيضا.
You see? This is what we're dealing with, okay?
فهمتم؟ وهذا ما نتعامل معه، حسنا؟
The third thing I will tell you
الشيء الثالث الذي سوف أقوله لكم
is that I also asked
هو أنا أيضاً سألت
for the directors of CL Financial,
لمديري مجموعة CL المالية،
whether in fact they were making filings under our Integrity in Public Life Act.
ما إذا كان في الواقع يقدمون الإيداعات بنزاهة "قانون الحياة العامة".
We have an Integrity in Public Life Act
لدينا نزاهة في "الحياة العامة قانون"
as part of our framework supposed to safeguard the nation's interest.
كجزء من النطاق المفترض لحماية مصالح الأمة.
And public officials are supposed to file
والموظفين العموميين من المفترض أن يرفعوا
to say what it is they have in terms of assets and liabilities.
مثلاً ما لديهم من حيث الأصول و الالتزمات.
And of course I've since discovered that they're not filing,
وطبعا لقد اكتشفت منذ ذلك الحين أنهم لم يودعون،
and in fact the Minister of Finance has not even asked them to file.
وفي الواقع "وزير المالية" لم يطلب منهم توثيق ذلك.
So here we have it. We have a situation where
لذا هنا لدينا. لدينا حالة فيها
the basic safeguards of integrity and accountability
الضمانات الأساسية للنزاهة والمساءلة
and transparency have all been discarded.
و الشفافية تم تجاهلها جميعاً.
I've asked the question in the legal and required fashion.
لقد سألت السؤال بطريقة قانونية ومطلوبة.
It's been ignored.
فتم تجاهلها.
The sort of thing that motivated us around Section 34,
هذا النوع من الأشياء التي دفعتنا الى قسم 34،
we need to continue to work on that. We can't forget it.
نحن بحاجة إلى مواصلة العمل على ذلك. لا يمكننا أن ننسى ذلك.
I have defined this as the single largest expenditure in the country's history.
قمت بتعريف هذا كأكبر نفقات في تاريخ البلاد.
It's also the single largest example
كما أنها أكبر مثال
of public corruption according to this equation.
على الفساد العام وفقاً لهذه المعادلة.
And this is my reality check.
وهذا هو إستقصائي بحثاً عن الحقيقة.
Where you have an expenditure of public money
حيث لدينا أنفاق للمال العام
and it is without accountability
و بدون مساءلة
and it's without transparency,
و بدون شفافية،
it will always be equal to corruption,
وسوف يكون دائماً مساوياً للفساد،
whether you're in Russia or Nigeria or Alaska,
سواء كنت في روسيا أو نيجيريا أو ألاسكا،
it will always be equal to corruption, and that is what we are dealing with here.
سوف يكون دائماً مساوياً للفساد، وهذا ما نتعامل معه هنا.
I'm going to continue the work
سوف أواصل العمل
to press on, to get some resolution
على الضغط، للحصول على بعض الحلول
of those matters at the Ministry of Finance.
لتلك المسائل في وزارة المالية.
If it is I have to go to court personally, I will do that.
إذا كان لا بد لي من الذهاب إلى المحكمة شخصياً، سوف أفعل ذلك.
We will continue to press on.
وسنواصل الضغط.
We will continue to work within JCC.
سوف نواصل العمل في إطار اللجنة المشتركة.
But I want to step back from the Trinidad and Tobago context
ولكن أريد أن أبتعد عن سياق ترينيداد وتوباغو
and bring something new to the table
وأحضر شيءٌ جديد
in terms of an international example.
فيما يتعلق بمثال دولي.
We had the journalist [Heather] Brooke speaking
أحضرنا الصحفيه هيذر بروك تتحدث
about her battle against government corruption,
عن معركتها ضد الفساد الحكومي،
and she introduced me to this website, Alaveteli.com.
وعرضت لي هذا الموقع، Alaveteli.com.
And Alaveteli.com is a way for us to have an open database
و Alaveteli.com طريقة لنا ليكون لديك قاعدة بيانات مفتوحة
for Freedom of Information applications,
لتطبيقات "حرية المعلومات"،
and speak with each other.
والتحدث مع بعضنا البعض.
I could see what you're applying for.
يمكن أن أرى ما قدمت الطلب من أجله.
You could see what I applied for and what replies I got.
ويمكنك أن تشاهد ما طلبت والردود التي حصلت عليها.
We can work on it together. We need to build a collective database
ويمكنا العمل على ذلك معاً. نحن بحاجة إلى بناء قاعدة بيانات جماعية
and a collective understanding of where we are to go to the next point.
وفهم جماعي لحيث نحن ذاهبين في النقطة التالية.
We need to increase the consciousness.
نحن بحاجة إلى زيادة الوعي.
The final thing I want to say is in relation to this one,
الشيء الأخير الذي أريد أن أقوله بالنسبة لهذا،
which is a lovely website from India
وهو موقع جميل من الهند
called IPaidABribe.com.
يسمى IPaidABribe.com.
They have international branches,
لديهم فروع دولية،
and it's important for us to tune into this one.
ومن المهم بالنسبة لنا أن نتجه إلى هذا.
IPaidABribe.com is really important,
IPaidABribe.com مهم حقاً،
a good one to log on to and see.
موقع جيد لتسجيل الدخول والنظر.
I'm going to pause there. I'm going to ask you for your courage.
سوف أقف هنا. وأطلب شجاعتكم.
Discard the first myth; it is a crime.
تجاهلوا الخرافة الأولى؛ أنها جريمة.
Discard the second myth; it is a big thing.
تجاهلوا الخرافة الثانية؛ شيء كبير.
It's a huge problem. It's an economic crime.
أنها مشكلة ضخمة. أنها جريمة اقتصادية.
And let us continue working together
ودعونا نواصل العمل معاً
to betterment in this situation,
للتحسين هذه الحالة،
stability and sustainability in our society. Thank you.
و الإستقرار والإستدامة في مجتمعنا. شكراً لكم.